[SPEAKER_00]: What were you saying?
[SPEAKER_00]: Any more realms of the God realm?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, the whole... the words... you know, brahmacharya is the way of... the holy life.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: The way of the gods.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, the way of the gods, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: The way of the brahmas.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the more... you know... Yeah, the cleaner, the more virtues, the loftier...
[SPEAKER_00]: The more God-life.
[SPEAKER_00]: The human life is lead.
[SPEAKER_00]: It becomes more God-life.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: The more proliferated, the more, based on senses, revolving around senses, absorbed in the senses, the more animal-like it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Based around sensual pleasures and gratification and so on, it's more like animals.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why the human choice, based on which you perform certain actions, awesome or not, kind of determines your future direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's a sort of realm in between that gives you a glimpse of both.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, animals don't have much... they're fully responsible, but they don't have much choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they suddenly can't behave like gods.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they can sometimes exhibit human-like behavior, which is already a big step forward for an animal.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, wow, look at that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And also, for gods, they can't behave.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's harder for them to behave like animals.
[SPEAKER_00]: But for humans, being kind of in between, we can get both, which is why the distinction is clear, which is why the human realm has both suffering and pleasure to such an extent that it's most optimal for practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: We get both, we can really recognize.
[SPEAKER_00]: Animals are just so deeply in pain, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Constant drive, constant fear, constant need.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not much reflection, so they don't really know anything better.
[SPEAKER_00]: Dogs, on the other hand, they're usually intoxicated with pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: They almost never experience pain, so they don't stop and think about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Human realm is exposed to both, and you kind of have the threat of the pain, of the suffering, but then you do have pleasure and gratification, which is also valid, valid phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's all, that's like the most optimal, to really develop wisdom.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's really, yeah, it's really effective on the... like just the animals.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just to watch a dog, you know?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just to see how agitated it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, like, you know, when you train, when you train a dog...
[SPEAKER_00]: In order to get it holistic, we have to get his attention.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, through a little repetition in training, you keep learning how to get his attention, and that's when you tell him, well, come on, and he always listens.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you realize how quickly that attention changes, and you know sometimes there's no point saying now, I don't have... like something else has taken.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, the well-trained dog would be able to be snagged out of whatever has taken his attention, no matter what.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that requires, you know, obviously, it depends on the brain and the skill of a trainer and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it all revolves.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when you do that, you notice how that attention is just all over the place, constant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sound, sound, smell, smell, touch, smell, smell, sound, sound, running, left, right, bite, ah, something, agitate, jump, calm, hungry.
[SPEAKER_00]: Constant.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's constant.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the enemy.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, you look at the little, cute little bird.
[SPEAKER_00]: You look at it, it's just constant terror, constant threats.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just keeps looking around, just twitching.
[SPEAKER_00]: Constantly twitching, because next moment, might be very last, there's some attack or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either birds, other praying animals, or things of that nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's just constantly... and that's the animal at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: Constant struggle, constant fight, constant survival.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, yeah, well, the other day we were... for some people like to get into... like, you hear this whole
[SPEAKER_02]: Getting into contact with the animal spirits and stuff like that, that whole... No, that's ridiculous.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, as if that the lion was kept, you know, the lion's got no fear or... You can use the simile.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can say the lion is the fearless, you become fearless, but you don't end with it in life.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you don't... Because what else is lion?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a killer, it's a murderer, it's a rapist.
[SPEAKER_00]: If that's what lions are, male lions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, when people glorify animals as if they kind of have some deeper sixth sense that we don't have... Yeah, they have their own ways of perception, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, they can detect subtler things, better smells, but that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not necessarily... it's not better, it's actually more proliferated, more particular, more based upon it, which means less reflection of power you have in regard to your senses, more you're pulled, driven, constant drive.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what animals are like.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, this whole kind of, you know,
[SPEAKER_00]: One with the nature, like, I must not interfere with the nature self.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's... that's quite silly, actually, because nature is what saṃsāra is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nature wants you to stay ignorant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nature is ignorant and it's all about ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not getting in touch with nature, becoming one with nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means becoming one with your ignorance, fully endorsing it as a valid... as a valid thing that should be cherished and protected.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because nature is what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And what it is, it's affected with the region.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, going against the stream means going against the nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: The nature of the body is to run after its, like, senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what the suttas say.
[SPEAKER_00]: Senses, five senses, are like five wild animals.
[SPEAKER_00]: They have their feeding grounds, and that's all they want to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: They just want to go and feed in their own feeding grounds.
[SPEAKER_00]: Eyes will pull you towards sights.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nose will pull you towards smell.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ears will pull you, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what your senses are.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what nature is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you actually go against that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Against the stream, against the grain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Are you going against the nature or are you understanding nature for what it is?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that means going against the nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, you know, there are different ways you can understand going against the nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: People can just take that to mean denying the nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: But again, in order to deny something, that thing has to be accepted first.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means denial of rebellion against nature is just confirmation of the nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: Full understanding, on the other hand, is truly going against it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like overcoming it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Swimming against the stream.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Going against needs to be clarified, like individually, and understood correctly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, there's everything else that pertains to dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't there is a... once a person has entered the stream, sotāpanna, stream entry, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Once someone has achieved sotāpanna, that's a guarantee that he wouldn't develop, that he wouldn't fall back to ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what do you mean exactly by that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Fall back.
[SPEAKER_00]: Define fall back.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, he would...
[SPEAKER_00]: He can't un-become, a sort of one.
[SPEAKER_00]: He can't become putrijan again.
[SPEAKER_00]: He can't have the personality of you and me.
[SPEAKER_01]: He can't.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: But anything below that... Well, he can break all the precepts, despite the popular belief.
[SPEAKER_00]: He can, you know, break all the precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: He cannot practice at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will require a lot of carelessness, lots of exposure to unwholesome circumstances for him to grow that bad, because he inherently possesses a criteria of wholesome, and has that permanently available view, right view, that he can effortlessly engage in.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's quite unlikely, but it's possible, as there were cases in the service of a drunken sotāpanna and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: We spoke about it before, I think, I spoke there with Tanya.
[SPEAKER_00]: The suttas mention clearly things that Sotāpanna cannot do, which is hold anything, any determination as permanent, any determination as pleasurable, anything presumed to be his self.
[SPEAKER_00]: He can't kill his mother, can't kill his father, can't kill an arahant, can't violate the bhikkhuni, can't disparage the Buddha or wound the Buddha, can't take anybody else other than the Buddha as his teacher.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's all changing.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can't follow any other teaching.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the dhamma is not just a view.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a recognition of the, like, a universal criteria.
[SPEAKER_00]: That it seems, you know, recognized, discerned, in your experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, once you discern that, those things are fundamental.
[SPEAKER_00]: Those things are universal.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's confirmed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, that becomes the
[SPEAKER_00]: The core criteria for everything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whenever you come across any other view, it's just going to be seen as either according to the universal principle, the right principle, or it doesn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you come across some other teaching, you will say, as a sotāpanna, you'll see, ah, this actually affords to the principles of the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, this teaching is dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or you see, you know, it doesn't have fault with dhamma, for such and such reasons, that's not dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: And by saying dhamma, it refers to that universal principle.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't have to call it Buddhism, because often, today, now, modern Buddhism, contemporary Buddhism, has nothing to do with the actual dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is the views that have evolved, wrong views, wrong methods, wrong principles, wrong techniques.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's a religion, product of society, ignorant society, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the dhamma, as a universal principle, stands and always will stand.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is why liberation always remains possible.
[SPEAKER_00]: As the Buddha says, like rediscovering an ancient path.
[SPEAKER_00]: He found the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like that has been worked before by others.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't get, ah, this...
[SPEAKER_00]: He didn't create anything, nor invent.
[SPEAKER_00]: He rediscovered and then reformulated.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, anyone that develops wisdom, but haven't attained a state, could develop it to a level that they'll fall back to saṃsāra continuously.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, what do you mean by state?
[SPEAKER_01]: As in sotāpanna?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, pratyūjana's wisdom, unless he develops it enough to cease to be a pratyūjana, he remains at risk.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why, as the Aniruddha pointed out, a person, really, a genuine person, genuinely interested in practice, you know, you really have to start thinking about, you know, like, developing right view as not an optional thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's your duty to become a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, all of your faculties, reasoning, powers of reflection are intact.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have no reason to not become a sotāpanna, except laziness and lack of effort, lack of commitment, lack of determination, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Absolutely no reason.
[SPEAKER_00]: Family, children, wives, husbands, none of that is actual excuse.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, people make an excuse out of that, so they won't feel guilty on account of not following the way out.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they absolve themselves from responsibility for the practice, for determination, for giving up, because they say, oh, well, I have a family, I have duties and stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it's a worldly duty, but this pertains to something much more.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, actually, the worldly duty can never serve as a reason or as an excuse.
[SPEAKER_00]: It just might require more of your determination, but then there is no excuse for not having more determination.
[SPEAKER_00]: Unless your faculties are impaired, you're mad, deranged or whatever else, then there's absolutely no excuse for not doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you stop and think about it, how many times have you been reborn?
[SPEAKER_00]: You might not know, but you can have a safe guess.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you have faith in the Buddha and trust in his words, he said how many times, countless times, eons and eons and eons and eons of rebirth in every possible realm that there was, there's nothing left unexperienced, unexplored, or anything like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you realize, well, from that point of view, and that's why the Buddha would talk about that, is from that point of view, you can actually
[SPEAKER_00]: Look at this entire life differently and realize, well, what is one life dedicated to dhamma?
[SPEAKER_00]: Nothing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, you know, now sometimes you feel, ah, well, I can't, like, give everything up in this life and just go and practice, because it just feels too much.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, from the perspective of only this life, it feels too much.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you start reflecting, like, from a greater point of view, you realize, well, what is one life?
[SPEAKER_00]: Dedicating one life, succeeding, maybe failing,
[SPEAKER_00]: Maybe partially succeeding.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, at least you know you tried.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, like, you know, you can believe in rebirth or not, or whatever else, but the point is you don't know those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: One thing you know for sure is you will die.
[SPEAKER_00]: And what if the Buddha was right when he was talking about rebirth and everything else?
[SPEAKER_00]: Are you willing to kind of
[SPEAKER_00]: Just bet on it, and gamble on it, and spend this life carelessly, doing whatever you want, whatever pleases you, and then the Buddha turns out to be right, and then you end up much worse, for like thousands of years.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, the chances of coming back up to human realm, once you fall lower into animal realm, for example, was like the blind sea turtle that comes out every 500 years,
[SPEAKER_00]: It just comes out to the top of the sea and goes down, so it doesn't linger.
[SPEAKER_00]: That turtle has... and then there is a yoke with a piece of wood with a hole in it, being thrown around by the, you know, great winds from the sea, left and right, everywhere.
[SPEAKER_00]: This turtle has a great chance of sticking its neck through that little hole.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then somebody who has fallen back onto the animal realm has a chance of coming back to human realm.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you consider that, and like, again, you can't have an empirical proof.
[SPEAKER_00]: Give me a scientific, well, it's because science is all based on senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're expecting to experience through your senses, as a proof, that which precedes your senses, rebirths and realms.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, if you just allow it as a valid possibility, you should then, out of... like, it will become obvious that the safe course of action would be, well, let me assume that there is, just in case that there is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because then, I'll be safe.
[SPEAKER_00]: Rather than gambling and just deciding that there isn't... Because there is no more proof that there is no rebirth, than there is a proof that there is rebirth.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, people say, well, I don't believe in rebirth.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're no more justified than those who believe in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you want to accept both and then recognize, well, I don't really know whether there is or there isn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, I should act just in case that there is, because if there is, I'll be much worse off if I behave as if there isn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: Wouldn't that be... wouldn't that same kind of argument be applied to a lot of different views?
[SPEAKER_00]: What do you mean?
[SPEAKER_01]: Just anything like, you know, whether it's a view about omnipresence or any sort of other philosophical or religious view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, this is not really a philosophical view.
[SPEAKER_00]: This clearly pertains something that precedes or comes after, succeeds after your existence that you know.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, it's truly metaphysical.
[SPEAKER_00]: It can't be experienced.
[SPEAKER_00]: It can be speculated about, and that's what you recognize.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is inherently never, can never go beyond the level of speculation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, I should act just in case.
[SPEAKER_00]: Choose a wise course of action.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, you know, views whether there is suffering and there is freedom of suffering, that's not metaphysical.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not like, you know, that can be speculative, but it can also be proven to yourself, fully understood, discerned, and confirmed.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, is that, as per Ślavarīpa, that I'm metaphysical?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, that's what the Buddha said, when he's at Vāyūna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Beyond experiment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't know, thus you should act.
[SPEAKER_00]: And actually, you don't even have to believe in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can just use your reasoning right here and now, that you do have, and just discern.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, in case there is a rebirth, it's actually better to behave here.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, plus, if I do behave here, people will like me here, respect me here, find me trustworthy here, because I'm a moral person
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm a virtuous person and they know they can rely on me.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then if there is a next life, great, then I win, like on both accounts.
[SPEAKER_00]: I win here, I win in the next life.
[SPEAKER_00]: If there is a next life, well, so be it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then we all end up the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: But at least here I live happily and respected by others and have my life smoother than if I'm a crook or criminal and always worrying being poor or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you really, you don't need a proof for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just use your own reasoning and recognize that it's better to act as if there is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's all that matters, how you act right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter whether there is or there isn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why I brought this up, because if you start thinking like that, you realize, what is dedicating this life, then, to the practice of dhamma?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's nothing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a small life.
[SPEAKER_00]: Big deal.
[SPEAKER_00]: You'll be dead anyway, and you know that for sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: And not in 50 years.
[SPEAKER_00]: Might be much sooner, might be much later.
[SPEAKER_00]: Point is, it will... it will happen.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it will come to an end.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, having your... spending your time pursuing mundane goals, of course, just... just plain gratification of your senses, just scratching your itch, you know that, even from the worldly point of view, that it doesn't amount to anything more than that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you're dead.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, your senses start breaking up.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't enjoy them anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything becomes rather unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your hearing goes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your body doesn't listen.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sickness sets in.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you're dead.
[SPEAKER_00]: And how you spend the life?
[SPEAKER_00]: Being completely controlled by those five wild animals, who just yanking you left and right, as they please.
[SPEAKER_00]: And now you're kind of stuck all too weak to do anything better, and then you die.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, if there is the next life, then you'll be really, really screwed.
[SPEAKER_02]: It is, obviously, what I've heard common, you know, just enjoy the life now.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just only what you can... wipe only what you have.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, just enjoy it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Do the best you can.
[SPEAKER_00]: But as I said, you don't even have to wait for the next life or so.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can see that that that view and logic, well, works only while you have your health, you have your youth, you have your life.
[SPEAKER_00]: And none of those things are guaranteed that you're going to have the very next moment.
[SPEAKER_00]: All of them are based upon a gratuitous assumption that you'll live forever, or at least for a long time, and that you will always be healthy.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, yeah, all... yeah, life is... life is happening so that you can go out and enjoy it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: But what about the person who's, you know, born with no legs or paralyzed?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or what about you just next day you find you have cancer?
[SPEAKER_02]: Does it work?
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't apply.
[SPEAKER_02]: Tell me now.
[SPEAKER_00]: How are you going to enjoy that?
[SPEAKER_00]: What happens to their view then, when you realize, oh, I'm subject to death?
[SPEAKER_00]: And now, it's confirmed.
[SPEAKER_02]: Those are there.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's a fact, that's for sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're going to die.
[SPEAKER_02]: What's going to happen afterwards is not...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what's the point?
[SPEAKER_02]: What's the point of life, you know, if you just say?
[SPEAKER_02]: If you have the view that this is all there is,
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, people who say that don't think very far, further than that, really.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, because if you think further than that, what... then what's the point of anything?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it really the point just to be enjoying... Again, as I just said, like, a few minutes ago, saying, like, those people having a view, this is all there is, well, that's something you decided as a view.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't know that for a fact.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're no more justified in deciding that, than deciding, no, this isn't what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And as it turns out, you're less justified.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's much less... much riskier course of assumption.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, this is all there is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do what you can, while you can.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you realize, well, what if this isn't all there is?
[SPEAKER_00]: And all my time that I had, I spent misbehaving and just running after like an animal, after any gratification I could get.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you end up much worse.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you want to consider it that you don't know whether this is all there is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, it's better to act as if it isn't all there is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, if there is something afterwards, those people who do say that there is something afterwards, they say, because of that, you should behave right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there is a good sense in that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you can see that for yourself, right here, right now, even as a Putrajana.
[SPEAKER_00]: Putrajanas can see that as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, obviously, if you want even more, if you want to be free from suffering right here, right now, let alone any future instances, then, yeah, you have to apply yourself even harder.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, again, it comes from the from the same perspective.
[SPEAKER_00]: Accepting the fact, well, rather recognizing the fact that one thing is sure is you will grow sick, age and die.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you know, spend your life enjoying your senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: Works when you're 20 years old.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you think you'll live forever...
[SPEAKER_00]: Mind you, you can be 50 years old and still say that, because you think you'll live forever, and you're healthy at the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, finally, a sick person, in a hospital, bedridden, saying that, holding that view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah, enjoy your life.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is great.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, I'm still alive, bedridden in a hospital, oozing out whatever else, I don't know, depending on the illness, I guess.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that person, would they be saying, oh, yeah, enjoy your senses while you're still alive?
[SPEAKER_02]: They might be telling others that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, they might.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, see, now I'm sick.
[SPEAKER_00]: Really make the most of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they might listen because the others are not sick.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're intoxicated with health.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you know that for yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everybody experienced that, more or less.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you're healthy, you don't care.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you get sick,
[SPEAKER_00]: Then you get all really worried, and then it's all... and you got sick because of your stupidity or foolishness, and then you make all those grand... you think, oh, I'll never do that again, you know.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you recover, and then you're back to the old ways you completely forgot.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's pure intoxication with what you have at the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like complete lack of mindfulness, absence.
[SPEAKER_00]: And same, you make grand plans and projects and
[SPEAKER_00]: And ideas and hopes and whatever else, just because you assume you will live forever, you assume your life will last for a long time.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you stop and think about that assumption, it's completely gratuitous, as every assumption is, but this one, it really can hit you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, as the Buddha said, even if somebody went forth and they don't achieve anything, but they don't disrobe, they stay, they keep the rules and they keep trying to practice, even if they don't get anywhere, even if they spend every single day for the rest of their life in tears, in pain, imposed by the restraint, it's still better than going back.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you've been around so long, so many times, that spending a third of your lifetime now, crying in pain, but holding that restraint, will actually contribute much more than just giving in to the senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, at the same time, you start to think, well, it's impossible to spend every single day for the rest of your life in tears and pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: No matter how great that pain is, it will fade.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you're ready for every single day of pain, anything less than that would be a blessing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And people, nobody likes restraint, because it feels like a chore, feels like an effort.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it feels like that only from the point of view where your sensuality feels effortless.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, the actual gratification of the senses might feel effortless, is effortless, but it never comes on its own.
[SPEAKER_00]: It always comes with a price.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's not seeing the connection between sensuality and gratification and the price and toll it takes.
[SPEAKER_00]: You reflect on the connection long enough, and it will become apparent because it is there, and then you realize it's much harder, much more taxing, much more... much more of a chore to be following your senses and enjoying them than saying no to the whole thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that connection needs to be dwelt on long enough until it becomes apparent, because it's not apparent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if it were apparent so easily, everybody would be free from sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you can start with a simple reflection of, if you're a layperson, living a household life, enjoying the pleasures of your senses, means pleasant tastes, touches, sounds,
[SPEAKER_00]: Finding a pleasant wife or a girlfriend, living a pleasant life.
[SPEAKER_00]: How do you achieve that?
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to work.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to earn.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to really put up with stuff you don't like, very often.
[SPEAKER_00]: You might find a work you like, you might be your own boss, but then you have to protect it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to fend off people who are the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: People who cheat on you, people who lie on you, people who want to take things away from you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there's always that risk.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you're committing your life to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're spending eighty... ninety percent of doing things you don't want, just so you get that five percent enjoyment.
[SPEAKER_00]: It... it doesn't... it doesn't... doesn't feel directly related to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the ignorance obscuring it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you realize that it's impossible to have enjoyment,
[SPEAKER_00]: Without 95% of pain revolving around it, directly or indirectly, you realize that enjoyment is not worth it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's when the when the Buddha talks about seeing the danger in the sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, by choosing to pursue the ways of the senses, which is basically choosing to have family, children, wives or husbands, whatever else, living that kind of life,
[SPEAKER_00]: You accept that whole sensual domain where these things pertain, where these things are.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means you don't practice restraint, but you practice pursuit.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's a form of commitment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Pursuing your senses is a form of commitment, but then you realize by accepting, by engaging in that pursuit, you make yourself liable to a great loss.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, say, you commit yourself to a pursuit of having a family, having children.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, now that you have family and children, you have to work harder for them, for the food, for the clothing, for the school.
[SPEAKER_00]: What if they get sick?
[SPEAKER_00]: What if they die?
[SPEAKER_00]: You spend twenty, thirty years cultivating, investing in those things, dedicating your whole life praising your children.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then they turn away on you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or they die, or an accident happened, and it just snatched away in a second.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you have not had say in that from the beginning.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, from the day one, you have no say in the destiny of your child.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you have no say in your own destiny, but you have ignored that when you decided to pursue the senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you reflect that, you realize that even the pursuit of the senses
[SPEAKER_00]: It's actually completely out of your hands.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why the suttas compare it to, like, climbing a tree.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, you see the ripe mangoes on the tree, so you climb the tree to eat them, to enjoy them.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then somebody else, while you're on top of that tree, comes, and he can't climb the tree, so he decides to cut it.
[SPEAKER_00]: While you're still on the top, he doesn't see or he doesn't care.
[SPEAKER_00]: He chops the tree, you fall down, break in it, and you're done.
[SPEAKER_00]: And pursue the senses,
[SPEAKER_00]: Exposes you to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Means going down, or climbing up the tree, or for kind, or the other, and something might come at a direct cross-purpose, and just snatch it away from you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Be it an accident, being other people, being both, who knows?
[SPEAKER_00]: The point is, the exposure is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there is the inherent danger in that pursuit.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you realize that danger is 95% of all.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it worth
[SPEAKER_00]: Risking your life, putting your head on a chopping block, when there is a good chance of axe falling down, just so you get that five percent thrill.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it is worth, that gratification is worth, for as long as you don't establish that connection between the two.
[SPEAKER_00]: i.e.
[SPEAKER_00]: for as long as you don't see the danger in some thrill.
[SPEAKER_00]: You establish the connection, and then the danger became apparent, the visible, the mind turned away, experience, dispassion, as the sūtras describe it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, like, the disgust became, well, real.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is danger, this is not what... mind turned away, never to go back to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it is like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: If sensuality and gratification would not inherently be dangerous,
[SPEAKER_00]: And risky, and much, like, much more revolving around pain than dissatisfaction.
[SPEAKER_00]: If it wouldn't be inherently that, then it wouldn't be unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that certainly freedom from it would not be possible.
[SPEAKER_00]: But because it is inherently dangerous, risky, and not worthy, it is inherently like that, then, by dwelling on that, freedom from it is possible.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you realize, saying no,
[SPEAKER_00]: As a form of restraint, the sensuality, it's 5% of effort, 95% of peace.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's well worth it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's when, when you find, when, when a person finds pleasure of renunciation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, actually, you, you experience pleasure by being, by recognizing strength that you have of saying no.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not being, you are stronger than senses, senses are not stronger than you.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's also a view that you will actually, through those challenges in life, through having a family child, eh, you will get to know yourself better.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: You will evolve.
[SPEAKER_00]: You will, you will evolve in a, in a way, in a, in a, in a, in a discovering different ways of pursuing the senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: But whether you evolve this way or that way, bottom line is, it's still within the nature of pursuing the senses, and that's still within the nature of that danger and risk.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, any evolving that you do will be within that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's basically like going in a muddy swamp and finding different ways to wash yourself with the muddy water.
[SPEAKER_00]: No matter how elaborate your ways become, it's still filthy water.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means you'll never be clean.
[SPEAKER_02]: Evolve in the same way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you know, you can be in prison, in prison, behind the locked door.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure, you can involve in that environment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever involving you do, it will be involving in the prison.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you really want to be as part of the prison.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's better to be uninvolved, out of the prison, than involved, in further comments, in the prison.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's not really involvement, it's just a further proliferation.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's people say that, they never say it
[SPEAKER_00]: For any other sense, any other purpose than a purpose of justifying their pursuit of the senses upon which they already decided.
[SPEAKER_00]: But now they need to keep justifying it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And sure, you can.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you do that to others because you might feel guilty or you might be... you might feel watched or judged.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you justify yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: But basically,
[SPEAKER_00]: That's done already when you're deeply down, committed to the senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, now you're just trying to make the best out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Cover up any doubt in regard to your choices, in regard to your commitment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Above all, absorb all the responsibility for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, well, you know, I can't.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can't go forth now because I have wife and children.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, they were not given to you, like, you know, out of nowhere.
[SPEAKER_00]: You've chosen wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, basically, what you're saying, you can't go forth, because of the choices you make, and the choices that you're still accepting.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can't... and that means you can't go forth, because you're choosing to not go forth.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, if you put it like that, you realize I'm fully responsible for not going forth, for not practicing the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, saying, oh, well, you evolve, you grow, by engaging in these challenges, it's like, well, you really grow by recognizing how to completely overcome those challenges so they don't arise.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why would you keep yourself in the environment where those challenges will be coming your way?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's silly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Surely, the wisdom is finding a place that's free from any challenge.
[SPEAKER_00]: But only a person who doesn't know how to free themselves from their challenges will say, no, no, no, challenges are good.
[SPEAKER_00]: They only say that because they don't know how to escape them, how to overcome them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they need to make themselves feel important or more valuable than they actually are.
[SPEAKER_02]: I remember we spoke a while back about seeing an attractive thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: I've seen... when you see an attractive object, like a car, I think, it feels painful by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Say, if I see... if I see a beautiful woman walking around in the city, I do...
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't dwell, I try not to dwell on this, but I know, I can see the beauty from the corner of my eye, can't I?
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't have to look at it, I can see it on the other side of the road.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then I have to restrain myself.
[SPEAKER_02]: But I was reflecting a bit further, like, that sign of beauty comes with pain somehow.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I was saying before.
[SPEAKER_00]: That sign of beauty is that which is painful.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not the restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's when you say no to a prospect of pleasure that is pulling you, whether it's a pleasurable sight, sound, smell, or any other sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: It feels like the pain has arisen because you said no.
[SPEAKER_00]: If only you go with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: The pain has arisen because you've been yanked by that animal of that sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just usually, you immediately go with it, so there is no yank.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, as the leash starts pulling you, you go with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there is no tension created.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you just feel smooth sailing, because you're just being driven.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, when you start reflecting on it, you sort of don't go instantaneously, and then there's a pain arising, and you think, oh, this pain has arisen,
[SPEAKER_00]: Because I didn't go immediately with this animal that pulled me.
[SPEAKER_00]: An animal of sight.
[SPEAKER_00]: But actually, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: You go a step further, and you realize, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: The pain has arisen because the stupid animal yanked me.
[SPEAKER_00]: And for as long as I go with it, it will keep yanking, because I'm allowing it to do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same, you take a dog on a leash, you let it yank your arm, and that's what you get used to.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, instead of going with it, you invest the effort to overpower that yank, so you actually control the animal.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, eventually, animal learns it's pointless to yank.
[SPEAKER_00]: I won't be let go when I yank.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, it listens.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, it goes where you direct it to go.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that needs to...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, the inevitable, oh, I've been yanked.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's because I didn't go with the animal as quickly as I should have.
[SPEAKER_00]: But no, you've been yanked because the animal pulled one.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you have to endure that initial pain and also see through it as not originating from you saying no to the animal that started to run with you holding onto its chain.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it has a reason because the animal has started... the animal is wild.
[SPEAKER_00]: The animal is untrained.
[SPEAKER_00]: The animal yanks.
[SPEAKER_00]: The eye goes towards that...
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: The eye goes for the sights.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when there is a pain of a pleasurable sight, it's because of the eye goes there, not because you're saying no to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hence, you stick to saying no to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Until, eventually, you overpower the eye, and it stops linking you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it realizes it's pointless.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, you tie the dog,
[SPEAKER_00]: To a post, it will yank and yank, and then... No.
[SPEAKER_00]: The post doesn't budge, doesn't break.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will sit down and calm down.
[SPEAKER_00]: And actually, that's the sutta simile.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you... like a strong post, you tie these five animals to a chain.
[SPEAKER_00]: They will go wild and try to pull the rope.
[SPEAKER_00]: When they can't break it, eventually, they'll quiet down and sit down.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you can take them off for a walk, and they'll be obedient.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the training of the senses.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, with the eye, you're going into the city, where it lights pretty, pretty girls, beautiful women.
[SPEAKER_02]: And, like I just said now, you see that it, you can see that it's not yours, because you realize that there's, all of a sudden, you're looking at this pretty girl on the other side of the road,
[SPEAKER_02]: But the whole time, your attention, your intention was, say, you're looking at the pavement, following you, or whatever, and then, all of a sudden, my whole, you know, my head turns, my vision turns to that specific thing, which I can say, yeah, that's attractive.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: From the hundreds of people walking around... Who are not attractive.
[SPEAKER_02]: Who are not attractive.
[SPEAKER_02]: I picked the one, which I'm not even looking at, who is attractive.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's because my eye
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not mine.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's seen more than...
[SPEAKER_00]: The eye wants that.
[SPEAKER_00]: The eye sees that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's the same, like, the same that Sutta was talking about yesterday, when Buddha asked the man, what do you think?
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is more numerous?
[SPEAKER_00]: Things that you haven't seen or things that you've seen?
[SPEAKER_00]: Things that you haven't seen, obviously.
[SPEAKER_00]: You use... because of that, you abandon all the things that you've seen.
[SPEAKER_00]: All the things that you will see will always be less numerous than things that are unseen.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus,
[SPEAKER_00]: But reflecting on that unseen, you can abandon everything that you've seen, and you will see.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the same sense, which is more numerous?
[SPEAKER_00]: Beautiful or ugly?
[SPEAKER_00]: Ugly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Out of a hundred people, you might find one or five attractive.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, they are of the same material, of the same make, like 95 unattractive ones.
[SPEAKER_00]: Old, sick, aging, overweight, whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: Things you don't find attractive, they're more numerous than the ones you pick as attractive.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you realize how circumstantial attractiveness is, and how random, and how exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nothing to do with you.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's entirely your eye finding this circumstantially pleasing.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you just run with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it pulls you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you don't know any better.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why Puthujjana can free himself from sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, that would already mean lots of wisdom.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's quite unlikely that a Puthujjana free from sensuality, that has come across Buddha's teaching, wouldn't discern enough to get the right view either.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, it's unlikely.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's kind of along the same way of abandoning assumptions.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it is possible, technically, saying they never heard dhamma instruction.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's possible.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because those things are obvious.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, not obvious, sorry.
[SPEAKER_00]: Those things can be discerned, can be made obvious.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is what sensuality is.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: And by going with it, you avoid the pain of the yank, of the pull.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Especially, imagine if you're a weak little man, have a massive
[SPEAKER_00]: Rottweiler, or even some crossbreed, some bullmastiff, powerful dog.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, you better go with it, because it will rip your arm off.
[SPEAKER_00]: But when you go with it... Well, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Go with it means you're gonna end up in the places you don't want to be.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Inevitably.
[SPEAKER_00]: You'll be dragged over things, just so you get a final satisfaction, what that wild animal wants.
[SPEAKER_00]: But 95% of it, you'll be dragged over thorns and bushes and
[SPEAKER_00]: And sharp rocks, and whatever else you have to put up with, just so you get that last moment of, ah, okay, I got what I want, and then another one, and then another one, and then another one, and then another one.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's much better, actually, to start developing your arms, so you can overpower the animal, rather than animal overpowering you.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will take time, but as any other strength development will, physical or mental, yeah, everything takes time, but it's worth it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And in this case, obviously, pertaining to the mind, it's... well, the benefits are immeasurable.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's one translation in the Sūtra Nibbāta, I don't know if to say it like this, but it says,
[SPEAKER_02]: Not guarding the doors... well, guarding the doors of the senses is quite good anyway.
[SPEAKER_02]: We said guarding the aperture of the senses.
[SPEAKER_02]: Apertures.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which, I don't know, it sounded quite nice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Where was that?
[SPEAKER_00]: A sutta?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, in Sutta Nipārtha.
[SPEAKER_02]: Someone just translated.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ah!
[SPEAKER_02]: Guarding the apertures of the senses.
[SPEAKER_02]: Nice.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which is... it just seemed a bit more...
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you can get that sense, or that sense of that door of the sense, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's all you're doing.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're not, you don't want to be pulled into it, into the abyss of that sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not, it's not like, you can't just go 24-7 saying no to everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just gonna, it's gonna collapse.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't, you can't sustain that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you discern when a dog is about to pull you, when a wild animal of your sense is about to pull you.
[SPEAKER_00]: What direction it's heading?
[SPEAKER_00]: Wholesome or unwholesome?
[SPEAKER_00]: Wholesome?
[SPEAKER_00]: Fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Go.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't go too fast.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't let it yank you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, be mindful, in other words.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, you have to eat.
[SPEAKER_00]: The animal of the taste will inevitably enjoy it, but you also have to eat.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you do let the animal go and eat, but you're mindful of it, to make sure it's not about enjoyment, it's about eating.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, you don't go, you don't, you don't have to go for the wild music parties, or, you know, even worse, take drugs, or immoral sexual behavior, or who knows what else.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't have to do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you don't let the animal go there.
[SPEAKER_00]: If animal is used to going there, which every animal is,
[SPEAKER_00]: It will hurt saying no to that anymore, because it will keep yanking me and yanking me and yanking me and yanking you.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you realize, well, it can't yank me forever, but if I do give in, well, it will end up yanking me for much longer.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you have 95% of pain revolving around, being dragged out of your control.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you can't stop.
[SPEAKER_00]: Once you, you know, like, when the thing yanks you,
[SPEAKER_00]: If you stand your ground still, you can withstand.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you give in, when the animal picks up more pace, more speed, then it's much harder to stop.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then you just have to wait for the crash and hope to survive the crash, and then restart again.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, tame bull elephant, like so many similes in the...
[SPEAKER_00]: Power is there, the pain, in full control.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, this is in regard to yourself, your own senses, which means, like, you know, teaching an animal, a dog, training it, to train it to listen to your voice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's identical.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to train yourself to listen to your voice, voice of reason, of wisdom, of discernment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, you know, people know, deep down, you know, whether you're just giving in, or whether you're going above it.
[SPEAKER_00]: As soon as you look, you know.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why, because you know, you feel guilty, and that's why you need to come up with those excuses that Tanya just listed, that people would often say.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ah, it's a real great odyssey, the real challenge.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's all nonsense.
[SPEAKER_00]: You do that only just to cover up your sense of guilt and responsibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know deep down inside, what are you doing, whether it's indulgent or not, whether it's wholesome or unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just have to listen.
[SPEAKER_00]: Learn how to listen to them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or rather, you have to make that voice powerful to override the pull of the senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when their voice says no, there is absolutely no debate.
[SPEAKER_00]: The animals stay still.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's far from impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: This just takes some effort.
[SPEAKER_00]: But everything takes effort.
[SPEAKER_00]: Being yanked by an animal takes effort of endurance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Pulling up with things.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's much worse, because you're not in control at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, sometimes it can take you down a way that ends up fatally, or much worse than what you anticipate, as people often do end up, based on sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: But saying no and investing in training your mind to be stronger than the senses, it's like, well, there's nothing dangerous about that.
[SPEAKER_00]: On the contrary, thus, even if you spend your entire life or the rest of your life in tears and pain of restraint, it's still more wholesome and more peaceful, actually, than being driven around by defiant wild enemies.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can teach them how to enjoy other things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: When they're prevented from going wild as far as they can, then they start enjoying what they have, what you give them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how it works.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's actually... there is another sutra where the Buddha says that you are
[SPEAKER_00]: Venerable Aniruddha says, practice jhānas, which is like the ultimate establishments of your mind, the strength that's developed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you develop jhānas, then the coarse rice that you're eating will feel like the finest hand-picked rice grains from, you know, the most, the richest curries.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the coarse rice would feel the finest.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's what you gave your mind, and that's when your mind got established, and now it finds tremendous contentment, and that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Contentment comes from the mind, doesn't come from from the prey that your animals chase and hunt.
[SPEAKER_00]: Comes from the chase and hunt.
[SPEAKER_00]: You prevent that, then they'll have to settle with what they have, and when they do, then you have even more.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then he said, practice jhānas because they, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: The coarse hemp robes that you wear will feel, will be perceived, as finest Tashmir silk.
[SPEAKER_00]: Practice jhānas, because sleeping on the root of tree or caves like this, where we are now, will feel like spending time in the fully plastered mansions, king's palaces.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the mind determines how it's gonna feel like.
[SPEAKER_00]: Undeveloped mind will need more to get any sense of gratification.
[SPEAKER_00]: Fully developed mind won't need any sensuality to get sense of content and gratification.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which people work for their whole lives.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're taking your whole life, slaving, you know, having a boss whom you hate, who is abusing you, make you do things you don't want, colleagues you don't trust.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just have friends.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, like even living with your family that you don't get on with.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a human life.
[SPEAKER_00]: You spend your whole life, why?
[SPEAKER_00]: For that 5% of the final, like itch, just wrinkling the itch-oak and bleeding out, but having a little sense of gratification of scratching it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just scratch, just a bit.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ignoring 95% of the mess you're creating, just because that tiny little scratch.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, compare that to the pleasure of somebody
[SPEAKER_00]: Whose itchy wounds have healed completely and he feels no itch whatsoever again, at all, ever again.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't even prepare.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you're right about that.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, I was thinking the other day too, and when I'm eating these vegetables and like brown rice and all of that, I'm enjoying it far much better than anything I used to have.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, you can see that, like, you can see that, like, you know, when you have a plate full of, or a table full of different plates of food, and you just, you know, go for the ones really you like, and the mind gets overly excited, or
[SPEAKER_00]: You kind of get some enjoyment, but it's not the same as if, like, when you're like this in the middle of the jungle, no village in sight, nothing, and then you have some plain food.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's all you have.
[SPEAKER_00]: It feels much more gratifying and satisfying than when you have a full plate of... full table of all sorts of plates and stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you're just so concerned about picking the wood exactly what you want, that you don't end up really appreciating any of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, if you only eat when you're hungry, then whatever you eat...
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you only eat when you're hungry, whatever you eat, you'll enjoy it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, I think there is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Actually, if you just try to fast for two days... Then, you know, the plainest cream crackers will go off, you know, when you haven't been eating for days.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's just like how far your animals have proliferated, how far they... you got used to going.
[SPEAKER_00]: As I said, you have a wild dog, he's just used to running around wherever he wants, but you can't expect him to be content sitting in one spot.
[SPEAKER_00]: He won't.
[SPEAKER_00]: He will be angry, mad.
[SPEAKER_00]: But he will calm down.
[SPEAKER_00]: Training.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why like the suttas are often about training, training yourself.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're becoming a master of your sense of room.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it's not, eh...
[SPEAKER_02]: Which means, then, you become a master of life.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, then, wisdom is easy.
[SPEAKER_00]: Where you're not being distracted.
[SPEAKER_00]: Pulled around, controlled by your senses, insight is just a matter of time.
[SPEAKER_02]: Right.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, you start to see way more things.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's obvious.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then you need very little instruction.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not a... you don't need a PhD or a degree of this name, a job to work yourself up.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you got your senses already.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, the senses got you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Changing that around... Well, yeah, all of the pursuits, worldly ambitions and stuff comes through the senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: Through wanting more for your senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, later on, security, safety, all of that comes... comes through being controlled by the senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: Living on that domain where those animals control you and pull you around, pull your pardon, as they please.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, sometimes people exhibit some restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: They say, oh, well, don't run out just now, wait, because then you can run further later.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it still pertains to the same run, same yank, same pull by the same animal with the same chain.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you really want to start addressing the nature of being pulled by your senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, you really want to start addressing the unwholesome thoughts and then controlling the wholesome ones.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, you know, you address that, then it becomes apparent that it wasn't... it was never you who was going after sights.
[SPEAKER_00]: It couldn't have been you, because sights pertain to your eyes.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why it's called saḷāyatana, six-sense space.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you have the five senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: And in the suttas, they're referred to as fields.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, these fields are where these sights run.
[SPEAKER_00]: Entertained to.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, your eyes go after the sights.
[SPEAKER_00]: By being constantly pulled, you just stop.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't even see that.
[SPEAKER_00]: All you see is me,
[SPEAKER_00]: And the stuff around, sights around, so you end up appropriate.
[SPEAKER_00]: You end up thinking you are those animals.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you start distinguishing, you realize there is no sight without this fleshy organ of my eyes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Inconceivable to have sights, to see sights, if there are no eyes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same for any other of the five senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: Inconceivable without a corresponding sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if it's inconceivable without, which means it's inseparable from, it's fully determined by, it's fully bound by, it's fully made by that, which means you and your sense of self is completely redundant.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that can be discerned even when you're not free from sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: But imagine how easy that would be to discern when you're not being driven around by those enemies.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then you just see, yeah, I have no interest in this at all, and now I have proven that to myself.
[SPEAKER_00]: I have confirmed it to myself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Better word than proven.
[SPEAKER_00]: I've confirmed for myself that I have no interest in it, because I'm in control, not the animals.
[SPEAKER_00]: And all you see is just pathetic animals trying to run left and right.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then even they will come down eventually.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then it becomes apparent, yeah, this was not mine to begin with.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if it were yours, you would have said it.
[SPEAKER_00]: If it were yours, those eyes would not be subject to destruction, subject to sickness, subject to death.
[SPEAKER_00]: You wouldn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: But they are.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means it's not yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't have it both.